The Lost Pharaoh: The Search for Akhenaten is a
documentary film directed by Nicholas Kendall.
Ancient pharaoh Akhenaten was almost lost to history.
Canadian archaeologist Donald Redford, who uncovered the foundation of one of the pharaoh’s many
temples, attempts to finally piece together this great Egyptian ruler’s enigmatic story.
Self - Narrator (voice), played by Donald Brittain.
Akhenaten (pronounced  ), also spelled Akhenaton or Echnaton (Ancient Egyptian: ꜣḫ-n-jtn ʾŪḫə-nə-yātəy, pronounced
[ˈʔuːχəʔ nə ˈjaːtəj] , meaning 'Effective for the Aten'), was an ancient Egyptian pharaoh reigning c.
1353–1336 or 1351–1334 BC, the tenth ruler of the Eighteenth Dynasty.
Originally named Amenhotep IV  (Ancient Egyptian: jmn-ḥtp, meaning "Amun is satisfied", Hellenized
as Amenophis IV), in the fifth year of his reign he adopted the name "Akhenaten".
As a pharaoh, Akhenaten is noted for abandoning traditional ancient Egyptian religion
of polytheism and introducing Atenism, or worship centered around Aten.
The views of Egyptologists differ as to whether the religious policy was absolutely
monotheistic, or whether it was monolatristic, syncretistic, or henotheistic.
This culture shift away from traditional religion was reversed after his death.
Akhenaten's monuments were dismantled and hidden, his statues were destroyed, and
his name excluded from lists of rulers compiled by later pharaohs.
Traditional religious practice was gradually restored, notably under his close successor
Tutankhamun, who changed his name from Tutankhaten early in his reign.
When, some dozen years later, rulers without clear rights of succession from the Eighteenth Dynasty founded a new dynasty, they
discredited Akhenaten and his immediate successors and referred to Akhenaten as "the enemy" or "that criminal" in archival records.
Akhenaten was all but lost to history until the late-19th-century discovery of Amarna,
or Akhetaten, the new capital city he built for the worship of Aten.
Furthermore, in 1907 a mummy that could be Akhenaten's was unearthed
from the tomb KV55 in the Valley of the Kings by Edward R.
Genetic testing has determined that the man buried in KV55 was Tutankhamun's
father, but its identification as Akhenaten has since been questioned.
Akhenaten's rediscovery and Flinders Petrie's early excavations at Amarna
sparked great public interest in the pharaoh and his queen Nefertiti.
He has been described as "enigmatic", "mysterious", "revolutionary", "the greatest idealist of the world", and
"the first individual in history", but also as a "heretic", "fanatic", "possibly insane", and "mad".
Public and scholarly fascination with Akhenaten comes from his connection with Tutankhamun, the unique style and high quality
of the pictorial arts he patronized, and the religion he attempted to establish, foreshadowing monotheism.
The film explores themes of ancient history, ancient egypt, archaeology.